I'm here to give you
أنا هنا لأقدم لكم
your recommended dietary allowance
الحصة الغذائية الموصى بها
of poetry.
من الشعر.
And the way I'm going to do that
و الطريقة التي سأفعل بها ذلك
is present to you
هي أن أقدم لكم
five animations
خمس رسوم متحركه
of five of my poems.
لخمس من قصائدي.
And let me just tell you a little bit of how that came about.
ودعوني أخبركم قليلا كيف بدأت هذه القصة.
Because the mixing of those two media
لأن مزج هذين النوعين من وسائل الإعلام
is a sort of unnatural or unnecessary act.
نوع من أنواع الفن غير المعتاد أو الغير ضروري.
But when I was United States Poet Laureate --
ولكن عندما كنت شاعر البلاط في الأمم المتحده
and I love saying that.
وأنا أحب قول ذلك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's a great way to start sentences.
إنها طريقة رائعة لبدأ الحديث.
When I was him back then,
عندما كنت ذلك الشخص سابقا
I was approached by J. Walter Thompson, the ad company,
لقد تم اكتشافي من قبل شركة الإعلان جيه والتر ثومبسون،
and they were hired
وقد تم تعينهم
sort of by the Sundance Channel.
نوعا ما عن طريق قناة سن دانس.
And the idea was to have me record some of my poems
والغرض من ذلك كان أن أسجل قصائدي
and then they would find animators
ومن ثم يبحثون عن رسوم متحركة
to animate them.
ليجعلوا القصيدة رسوماً متحركة.
And I was initially resistant,
في البداية رفضت،
because I always think
لأني كنت أفكر دائماً
poetry can stand alone by itself.
الشعر يمكن أن يكون عملا مميزاً في حد ذاته.
Attempts to put my poems to music
محاولات وضع موسيقى علي قصائدي
have had disastrous results,
كانت كارثية،
in all cases.
في جميع الأحوال.
And the poem, if it's written with the ear,
والقصيدة، اذا كتبت للتماشى مع الأذن،
already has been set to its own verbal music
في هذه الحالة سيكون لها موسيقاه الخاصة
as it was composed.
بالطريقة التي كُونت بها.
And surely, if you're reading a poem
وبالطبع، عندما تقرأ قصيدة
that mentions a cow,
يُذكر فيها بقرة
you don't need on the facing page
فأنت لست بحاجة ليكون أمامك
a drawing of a cow.
رسمة لبقرة.
I mean, let's let the reader do a little work.
أقصد، فلنترك للقارئ القليل من العمل.
But I relented because it seemed like an interesting possibility,
إلا انني رضخت لأنها بدت كاحتمالية مثيرة،
and also I'm like a total cartoon junkie
وكوني مُدمن علي الرسوم المتحركة
since childhood.
منذ الصغر.
I think more influential
أظن أنا ما كان أكثر تأثيراً
than Emily Dickinson or Coleridge or Wordsworth
من إيميلي داكنسون أوكولريدج أووردزورث
on my imagination
علي مُخيلتي
were Warner Brothers, Merrie Melodies
كانوا وارنر بروذرز، ميري ميلوديز
and Loony Tunes cartoons.
ولوني تيونز بما صنعوه من أفلام متحركة.
Bugs Bunny is my muse.
بجز باني هو متعتي
And this way poetry could find its way onto television of all places.
هكذا يمكن للشعر أن يجد طريقه إلي التلفاز و إالي كل الأماكن.
And I'm pretty much all for poetry in public places --
وكل هدفي أن يصبح الشعر موجوداً في الاماكن العامة--
poetry on buses, poetry on subways,
أن يصبح علي عربات النقل العام، وفي الأنفاق،
on billboards, on cereal boxes.
وعلي لوحات الإعلانات، وعبوات حبوب الإفطار.
When I was Poet Laureate, there I go again --
عندما كنت شاعر البلاط، ها أنا أقولها مجدداً--
I can't help it, it's true --
لا أستطع منع نفسي،هذا حقيقي--
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I created a poetry channel on Delta Airlines
أنشأت قناة لبث الشعر على خطوط دلتا الجوية
that lasted for a couple of years.
التي أبقيتها لعدة أعوام.
So you could tune into poetry as you were flying.
حتي يمكنك الاستماع إلي الشعر أثناء رحلتك.
And my sense is,
وشعوري،
it's a good thing to get poetry off the shelves
أنه من الجيد أن تنقل الشعر من علي الأرفف
and more into public life.
ليتوغل أكثر في الحياة العامة.
Start a meeting with a poem. That would be an idea you might take with you.
أن تجتمع مع قصيدة، يمكن أن يلهمك بفكرة
When you get a poem on a billboard or on the radio
عندما تجد قصيدة على لوحة الإعلانات أو على المذياع
or on a cereal box or whatever,
أوعلى علبة حبوب الإفطار أو أياً كان،
it happens to you so suddenly
سوف يحدث ذلك فجأة
that you don't have time
لدرجة أنك لن تجد الوقت
to deploy your anti-poetry deflector shields
لنشر دروعك المضادة للشعر
that were installed in high school.
التي أعددتها منذ المدرسة الثانوية.
So let us start with the first one.
لذا فلنبدأ بأول قصيدة.
It's a little poem called "Budapest,"
إنها قصيدة صغيرة تدعى"بودابست،"
and in it I reveal,
اكتشف فيها،
or pretend to reveal,
أو ادعي أني اكتشفت،
the secrets of the creative process.
سر الأعمال الإبداعية.
(Video) Narration: "Budapest."
(فيديو) سرد قصصي: "بودابست."
My pen moves along the page
قلمي يتحرك علي طول الصفحة
like the snout of a strange animal
كأنف حيوان غريب
shaped like a human arm
شُكل علي هيئة ذراع إنسان
and dressed in the sleeve
ويرتدي ملابس ذات أكمام
of a loose green sweater.
لسترة فضفاضة خضراء اللون.
I watch it sniffing the paper ceaselessly,
أراها تشتم الورق بلا كلل،
intent as any forager
بغرض حفظ المؤن
that has nothing on its mind
لا يخطر شئ ببالها
but the grubs and insects
غير اليرقات و الحشرات
that will allow it to live another day.
التي ستجعلها تحيا ليوم جديد
It wants only to be here tomorrow,
لا تنشد غير البقاء هنا غدا،
dressed perhaps
ربما ترتدي
in the sleeve of a plaid shirt,
قميصاً ذو نقوش مربعة،
nose pressed against the page,
وبأنف منكب علي الورقة،
writing a few more dutiful lines
يكتب بضعة سطور عليه أن يكتبها
while I gaze out the window
بينما أنا سارحٌ في النافذة
and imagine Budapest
أتخيل بودابست
or some other city
أو مدينة أخرى
where I have never been.
لم أزورها من قبل.
BC: So that makes it seem a little easier.
هكذا يبدو الأمر أسهل قليلاً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Writing is not actually as easy as that for me.
في الواقع الكاتبة ليست بالشئ الهين بالنسبة لي
But I like to pretend that it comes with ease.
لكني أحب أن ادعي أنها كانت سهلة.
One of my students came up after class, an introductory class,
واحدة من طلابي جائت بعد انتهاء الدرس، درس المقدمة،
and she said, "You know, poetry is harder than writing,"
وقالت، "أتعلم، الشعر أصعب من الكتابة،"
which I found both erroneous and profound.
فوجدت كلامها خاطئ وعميق معاً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I like to at least pretend it just flows out.
لذلك أحب أن أدعي أنه يتدفق بمفرده.
A friend of mine has a slogan; he's another poet.
لدي صديق يحمل شعاراً؛ وهو شاعر أيضاً
He says that, "If at first you don't succeed,
يقول،"إذا لم تنجح من البداية،
hide all evidence you ever tried."
خبئ كل الأدلة علي محاولاتك."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The next poem is also rather short.
القصيدة التالية قصيرة أيضاً.
Poetry just says a few things in different ways.
الشعر يقول بعض الأشياء بطرق مختلفة فقط.
And I think you could boil this poem down to saying,
وأظن أن مغزي هذه القصيدة هو،
"Some days you eat the bear, other days the bear eats you."
"قد تأكل الدب أحياناً، وقد يأكلك الدب أحياناً أخرى"
And it uses the imagery
وهي تستخدم صورة تخيلة
of dollhouse furniture.
لأثاث دمية.
(Video) Narration: "Some Days."
(فيديو) سرد قصصي:"أحياناً."
Some days
أحياناً
I put the people in their places at the table,
أضع الناس في أماكنهم على الطاولة،
bend their legs at the knees,
وأثني أرجلهم من عند الركبة،
if they come with that feature,
إذا أتوا على هذه الحالة،
and fix them into the tiny wooden chairs.
وأثبتهم على الكراسي الخشبية الصغيرة.
All afternoon they face one another,
والجميع بعد الظهيرة يجلس مع بعضهم البعض،
the man in the brown suit,
الرجل ذو الحلة البنية،
the woman in the blue dress --
المرأة ذات الثوب الأزرق--
perfectly motionless, perfectly behaved.
بلا حراك تماماً، ويتصرفون بمثالية.
But other days I am the one
لكن في أيام أخرى أكون أنا
who is lifted up by the ribs
من يُحمل من الأضلاع
then lowered into the dining room of a dollhouse
ومن ثم أُوضع علي طاولة عشاء بيت الدمى
to sit with the others at the long table.
لأجلس مع الأخرين علي الكراسي الطويلة.
Very funny.
مضحك جداً.
But how would you like it
لكن كيف سنتصرف
if you never knew from one day to the next
إذا لم تعرف أنه من يوم لأخر
if you were going to spend it
إذا كنت ستمضيه
striding around like a vivid god,
تختال كإله حي،
your shoulders in the clouds,
كتفاك في السماء،
or sitting down there
أو جالساً هناك
amidst the wallpaper
داخل اللوحة
staring straight ahead
تحدق أمامك مباشرة
with your little plastic face?
بوجهك البلاستيكي الصغير؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
BC: There's a horror movie in there somewhere.
يوجد فيلم رعب هنا في مكان ما.
The next poem is called forgetfulness,
القصيدة التالية تدعى نسيان
and it's really just a kind of poetic essay
وهي في الحقيقة نوع من الشعر المقالي
on the subject of mental slippage.
في موضوع الانزلاق العقلي.
And the poem begins
والقصيدة تبدأ
with a certain species of forgetfulness
بنوع محدد من من النسيان
that someone called
الذي يسمونه البعض
literary amnesia,
حرفياً فقدان الذاكرة،
in other words, forgetting the things that you have read.
بطريقة أخرى، نسيان الأشياء التي قرأتها.
(Video) Narration: "Forgetfulness."
(فيديو)سرد قصصي:"نسيان."
The name of the author is the first to go,
أول ما يُنسى هو إسم المؤلف،
followed obediently
يُتبع بطاعة
by the title, the plot,
بالعنوان،والحبكة،
the heartbreaking conclusion,
تليها النهاية المؤلمة،
the entire novel,
ثم الرواية بأكملها،
which suddenly becomes one you have never read,
التي تصبح فجأة رواية لم تقرأها من قبل،
never even heard of.
ولم تسمع بها من قبل.
It is as if, one by one,
كأنها، واحدة تلو الأخرى
the memories you used to harbor
الذكريات التي كنت تحتفظ بها
decided to retire to the southern hemisphere of the brain
قررت أن تتقاعد في النصف الجنوبي من مخك
to a little fishing village
إلي بحيرة صيد صغيرة
where there are no phones.
حيث لا يوجد هواتف.
Long ago,
قديماً،
you kissed the names of the nine muses good-bye
قبلت أسماء آلهة الإبداع التسعة مودعاً
and you watched the quadratic equation
وشاهدت المعادلة التربيعية
pack its bag.
تحزم أمتعتها.
And even now,
وحتى الآن،
as you memorize the order of the planets,
حينما تذكر ترتيب الكواكب
something else is slipping away,
شئ أخر ينزلق بعيداً،
a state flower perhaps,
ربما زهرة الزهرة،
the address of an uncle,
عنوان أحد أعمامك،
the capital of Paraguay.
عاصمة البارغواى
Whatever it is
أياً كان هذا الشئ
you are struggling to remember,
أنت تعاني لتتذكره،
it is not poised on the tip of your tongue,
وهو ليس علي حافة لسانك،
not even lurking
ولا حتى مختبئ
in some obscure corner
في ركن غامض
of your spleen.
من طحالك.
It has floated away
لقد طفى بعيداً
down a dark mythological river
أسفل نهر أسطوري مظلم
whose name begins with an L
الذي يبدأ إسمه بحرف اللام
as far as you can recall,
حسب ما تذكر،
well on your own way to oblivion
حسناً في طريقك إلي النسيان
where you will join those
حيثما تنضم إلي أولئك
who have forgotten even how to swim
الذين نسوا كيفية السباحة حتى
and how to ride a bicycle.
وكيف يركبون الدراجة.
No wonder you rise in the middle of the night
لا عجب في أنك تستيقظ في منتصف الليل
to look up the date of a famous battle
لتبحث عن تاريخ معركة شهيرة
in a book on war.
في كتاب عن الحرب.
No wonder the Moon in the window
لا عجب في أن القمر في الشباك
seems to have drifted out of a love poem
يبدو وكأنه انسل من قصيدة عاطفية
that you used to know by heart.
كنت تحفظها عن ظهر قلب.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
BC: The next poem is called "The Country"
القصيدة التالية تدعى"الريف"
and it's based on,
وهي مقتبسة عن،
when I was in college
عندما كنت في الجامعة
I met a classmate who remains to be a friend of mine.
قابلت رفيق بقى صديقاً لي
He lived, and still does, in rural Vermont.
كان يعيش ،ولا يزال، في فيرمونت الريفية.
I lived in New York City.
أنا عشت في مدينة نيويورك.
And we would visit each other.
وكنا نزور بعضنا البعض.
And when I would go up to the country,
وعندما كنت أذهب إلي الريف،
he would teach me things like deer hunting,
كان يعلمني أشياء كصيد الغزلان،
which meant getting lost with a gun basically --
والتي تعني مبدئيا أن تتوه ومعك بندقية--
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
and trout fishing and stuff like that.
وصيد السلمون وأشياء مثل ذلك.
And then he'd come down to New York City
من ثم جاء هو إلي مدينة نيويورك
and I'd teach him what I knew,
وكنت أعلمه ما أعرفه،
which was largely smoking and drinking.
والذي كان في الغالب شرب الخمر والتدخين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And in that way we traded lore with each other.
وبهذه الطريقة تبادلنا التقاليد مع بعضنا البعض.
The poem that's coming up
القصيدة التالية
is based on him trying to tell me a little something
مبنية على محاولاته تعليمي بعض
about a domestic point of etiquette
آداب التصرف
in country living
في الحياة الريفية
that I had a very hard time, at first, processing.
التي أمضيت وقت صعب في تعلمها، في البداية.
It's called "The Country."
وتدعى "الريف"
(Video) Narration: "The Country."
(فيديو) سرد قصصي: "الريف"
I wondered about you
تعجبت منك
when you told me never to leave
عندما أخبرتني ألا أترك
a box of wooden strike-anywhere matches
علبة الثقاب سريعة الاشتعال في أي مكان
just lying around the house,
في أرجاء المنزل،
because the mice might get into them
لأن الفئران قد تصل إليها
and start a fire.
وتحدث حريقاً
But your face was absolutely straight
لكن وجهك كان صارماً للغاية
when you twisted the lid down
عندما أغلقت غطاء
on the round tin
العلبة المستديرة
where the matches, you said, are always stowed.
حيث تُحفظ عيدان الثقاب كما قولت.
Who could sleep that night?
من يستطع ينام في تلك الليلة؟
Who could whisk away the thought
من يمكن أن يتوارد إلي ذهنه
of the one unlikely mouse
أن فأرً في الجوار
padding along a cold water pipe
يتجول في مصورة مياه باردة
behind the floral wallpaper,
خلف ورق الحائط ذو الورود،
gripping a single wooden match
أن يسحب عود ثقاب
between the needles of his teeth?
بين ثنايا أسنانه؟
Who could not see him rounding a corner,
من قد لا يرى الفأر في الأرجاء،
the blue tip scratching against rough-hewn beam,
والحافة الزرقاء تحتك بلوح الخشب الخام،
the sudden flare
الشرارة المفاجأة
and the creature, for one bright, shining moment,
وهذا الكائن، وللحظة مضيئة ومشرقة،
suddenly thrust ahead of his time --
فجأةً يتفوق علي زمانه--
now a fire-starter,
الآن هو مُشعل النار،
now a torch-bearer
الآن هو حامل الشعلة
in a forgotten ritual,
في طقوس منسية،
little brown druid
هذا الكاهن الصغير بني اللون
illuminating some ancient night?
يضئ ثمة ليلة قديمة؟
And who could fail to notice,
ومن يمكن أن يفشل في ملاحظة،
lit up in the blazing insulation,
تلك النظرات المشتعلة،
the tiny looks of wonderment
نظرات الدهشة الصغيرة
on the faces of his fellow mice --
علي وجه أتباعه من الفئران--
one-time inhabitants
سكان ولو لمرة واحدة
of what once was your house in the country?
لشئ كان يدعى بيتك في الريف؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
BC: Thank you.
شكراً لكم
Thank you. And the last poem is called "The Dead."
شكراً لكم، والقصيدة الاخيرة تُدعى"الأموات"
I wrote this after a friend's funeral,
كتبتها بعد جنازة أحد أصدقائي،
but not so much about the friend as something the eulogist kept saying,
لكنها ليست عن صديقي بقدر كونها عن شئ ما يقولونه المادحون دوماً
as all eulogists tend to do,
وكما يحاول المادحون دائماً قول
which is how happy the deceased would be
كم سيصبح المُتوفى سعيداً
to look down and see all of us assembled.
عندما ينظر للأسفل ويرى تجمعنا.
And that to me was a bad start to the afterlife,
وهذا بالنسبة لي بداية سيئة للآخرة،
having to witness your own funeral and feel gratified.
أن ترى جنازتك وتشعر بالامتنان.
So the little poem is called "The Dead."
لذا هذه القصيدة تُدعى" الأموات"
(Video) Narration: "The Dead."
(فيديو) سرد قصصي:"الأموات"
The dead are always looking down on us,
الأموات دوماً يراقبوننا،
they say.
كما يقولون.
While we are putting on our shoes or making a sandwich,
بينما نحن نرتدي الحذاء أو نُعد شيطرة،
they are looking down
هم يراقبوننا
through the glass-bottom boats of heaven
عبر قوارب السماء زجاجية القاع
as they row themselves slowly
بينما هم يجذفون ببطئ
through eternity.
نحو الأزلية.
They watch the tops of our heads
يشاهدون قمم رؤسنا
moving below on Earth.
تتحرك في الأسفل على الأرض.
And when we lie down
وعندما نستلقي
in a field or on a couch,
في الحقول أو على الأريكة،
drugged perhaps
مُخدرين في الغالب
by the hum of a warm afternoon,
تحت تأثير دندنات ظهيرة دافئة،
they think we are looking back at them,
يعتقدون أننا ننظر إليهم بالمقابل،
which makes them lift their oars
الشئ الذي يجعهلم يتركون مجاذيفيهم
and fall silent
ويصمتون
and wait like parents
كالآباء وهم ينتظرونا
for us to close our eyes.
لنغلق أعيننا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
BC: I'm not sure if other poems will be animated.
أنا لست متأكداً حيال تكرار هذه الفكرة
It took a long time --
لقد استغرقت وقتاً طويلاً--
I mean, it's rather uncommon to have this marriage --
أعني، أن هذا المزيج غير شائع--
a long time to put those two together.
مضى وقت طويل لمزج هاتين معاً
But then again, it took us a long time
ولكن مجدداً، لقد استغرقت وقتاً طويلاً
to put the wheel and the suitcase together.
لوضع العجلات و الحقائب معاً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I mean, we had the wheel for some time.
أعني، لقد امتلكنا العجلة لبعض الوقت.
And schlepping is an ancient and honorable art.
والتلكأ فن قديم ومحترم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I just have time
أنا امتلك الوقت
to read a more recent poem to you.
لقراءة قصيدة حديثة لكم.
If it has a subject,
إذا كانت تمتلك موضوع،
the subject is adolescence.
الموضوع عن المراهقة.
And it's addressed to a certain person.
وهو مخصص لشخص معين
It's called "To My Favorite 17-Year-Old High School Girl."
يُدعى"إلي فتاتي المفضلة ذات 17 عاماً."
"Do you realize that if you had started building the Parthenon
"هل تدركين أنكِ إذا بدأتي ببناء البارثينون
on the day you were born,
منذ يوم ولادتك،
you would be all done in only one more year?
أنه سوف يكون مكتملاً بحلول العام القادم؟
Of course, you couldn't have done that all alone.
بالطبع، لم يكن بستطاعتك فعل هذا كله بمفردك.
So never mind;
لذا لا عليك؛
you're fine just being yourself.
أنتِ بخير لمجرد كونك أنتِ.
You're loved for just being you.
أنتِ محبوبة لمجرد كونك أنتِ.
But did you know that at your age
لكن هل تعرفين أنه في عمرك
Judy Garland was pulling down 150,000 dollars a picture,
جادي جيرلاند كانت تحصل علي 150000 دولار مقابل لوحة
Joan of Arc was leading the French army to victory
جون أوف أرك يقود الجيش الفرنسي للنصر
and Blaise Pascal had cleaned up his room --
و بليس باسكال نظف غرفته--
no wait, I mean he had invented the calculator?
بدون انتظار، اعني لقد اخترع الآلة الحاسبة؟
Of course, there will be time for all that
بالطبع، سيكون هناك متسع من الوقت لكل هذا
later in your life,
لاحقاً في الحياة،
after you come out of your room
عندما تخرجين من غرفتك
and begin to blossom,
وتبدأين في الازدهار،
or at least pick up all your socks.
أو علي أقل تقدير بعد أن ترتبي جواربك .
For some reason I keep remembering
لسبب ما استمر بتذكر
that Lady Jane Grey was queen of England
أن السيدة جان جراى كانت ملكة إنجلترا
when she was only 15.
عندما كانت بعمر 15 فقط.
But then she was beheaded, so never mind her as a role model.
لكن بعدها قٌطع رأسها، لذا لا تتخذيها كمثال يحتذى به أبداً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
A few centuries later,
بعد عدة عقود لاحقة،
when he was your age,
عندما كان بمثل عمرك،
Franz Schubert was doing the dishes for his family,
فرانز شوبيرت كان يغسل صحون عائلته،
but that did not keep him
لكن هذا لم يمنعه
from composing two symphonies, four operas
من تأليف سيفونيتين، أربعة معزوفات أوبرلاية
and two complete masses as a youngster.
وقداسان كاملان وهوشاب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But of course, that was in Austria
لكن بالطبع، كان هذا في النمسا
at the height of Romantic lyricism,
في ذروة عصر الأغاني الرومانسية،
not here in the suburbs of Cleveland.
ليس هنا في أحياء كليفيلاند
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Frankly, who cares
صدقاً، من يهتم
if Annie Oakley was a crack shot at 15
إذا كانت آني أوكلي قُتلت في 15 من عمرها
or if Maria Callas debuted as Tosca at 17?
أو إذا ظهرت مايا كالاس بشخصية توسكا في ال17؟
We think you're special just being you --
نحن نعتقد أنكِ مميزة لمجرد كونك أنت--
playing with your food and staring into space.
وأنت تلعبين بطعامك وتحدقين في الفراغ
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
By the way,
بالمناسبة،
I lied about Schubert doing the dishes,
لقد كذبت بشأن شوبيرت وهو يغسل الصحون،
but that doesn't mean he never helped out around the house."
لكن هذا لا يعني أنه لم يكن يساعد في الأعمال المنزلية."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you. Thank you.
شكراً لكم. شكراً لكم.
Thanks.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)